A Finding Aid to the Jacques Lipchitz papers and Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1910-2001, bulk 1941-2001, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1961-2001; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 43.3 Linear feet Boxes 13-67, OV 68-69
  - Film Projects Regarding Jacques Lipchitz, 1971-2001; 2.5; Archival Resource Key; 28.2 Linear feet Boxes 22-46, 53-65, OV 69
    - Jacques Lipchitz Interactive Project, 1972-2001; 2.5.2; Archival Resource Key
      - Audiovisual Materials, Archival Resource Key
        - Segments, continued, Archival Resource Key
          - Unidentified Segments, circa 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key; 13 Film reels soundtrack, in 2 film cans (Item FC 200-210)
            - Monumental Doings and Final Sound Statement Alt., reel 1, 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 198)
            - Florida (sound), reel 2, 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 199)
      - Demonstrations, Archival Resource Key
        - Metropolitan Museum, 1972 June 11; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - City University of New York, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 29, Folder 2)
        - Exxon Education Foundation, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 29, Folder 3-4)
          script and 1 videocassette: U-Matic
      - Exhibition Materials, Archival Resource Key
        - Magnetic Strips, circa 1971-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 29, Folder 5)
          in shoebox
        - Segment Boards, circa 1972-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 29, Folder 6)
          Oversized item in OV 69
        - Signs, circa 1972-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 29, Folder 7)
        - Topic Cards, circa 1972-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 29, Folder 8)
      - Production Notebooks, circa 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 29, Folder 9)
      - Production Files, circa 1972-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 29, Folder 10-13)
      - Program Code, circa 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 29, Folder 14-15)
      - Program Guide, 1998-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 29, Folder 16)
      - Questions and Answers, Archival Resource Key
        - Handwritten Question Cards, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 30, Folder 1-6)
        - Printouts of All Questions, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 30, Folder 7-8)
        - Printouts of Questions with Answers, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 30, Folder 9-12)
        - Printed Questions on Sorting Cards, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 30, Folder 13-15)
        - Annotated Questions, circa 1972-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 1-2)
        - Coded Questions, circa 1972-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 3-4)
      - Source Book, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 5)
      - Source Book, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 6)
      - Source Book, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 7)
      - Source Book, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 8)
      - Source Book, circa 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 9-11)
      - Source Book, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 12-14)
      - Source Book, Krannert Art Museum, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 15-16)
      - Source Book, Reels A-D and Parts I and II Revised Script, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 17)
      - Technical Drawings of Interactive System, circa 1972-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 18)
      - Transcript of Picasso Segment, circa 1972-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 31, Folder 19)
      - Oversized Exhibition Materials, Segment Board and Signs (from Box 38, items 6-7), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 69)
    - Jacques Lipchitz Documentary, 1972-1994; 2.5.3; Archival Resource Key
      This subseries contains audiovisual and a few paper records related to the documentary Bassett produced about Jacques Lipchitz. The first version was created in 1972 in tandem with the Metropolitan Museum of Art's Lipcthiz retrospective exhibition. The documentary was updated in 1977 with footage added from the posthumous large-scale sculpture installations, and then revised again in 1991.
      The subseries includes multiple finished versions of the documentary in their presentation and distribution formats (film and video), and pre-print master elements of the finished versions (A+B roll and internegative; master from which distribution copies are made). Also found are production elements made at different stages of production and revision, excerpts of the finished film compiled for publicity, and two pieces of television coverage of the installation of Bellerophon Taming Pegasus that use Bassett's footage.
      Some of the film cans contain paper lab records for prints and edits created over the years.
      Additional records related to the documentary are found in Subseries 2.2.1 Business Records, Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation, and Subseries 2.3, Printed Materials.
      One copy of the documentary has been digitized for research use.
      - Finished Versions, Archival Resource Key
        - Presentation Copy, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 28, Folder 7-8)
        - Presentation Copy, 1977; Archival Resource Key
          - Presentation Copy reel 1, 1977; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 211)
          - Presentation Copy reel 2, 1977; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 212)
        - Presentation Copy, 1977 and 1983; undated; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 32, Folder 1-2)
        - Presentation Copy, Short Version, 1989; Archival Resource Key
          - Presentation Copy, Short Version, 1989; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel (Item FC 309)
          - Presentation Copy, Short Version, 1983; 1989; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (2 duplicate videocassettes: U-Matic and VHS); 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 32, Folder 3-4)
        - Presentation Copy, 1991; Archival Resource Key
          - Presentation Copy, 1991; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 310)
          - Presentation Copy, 1991; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic); 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 32, Folder 5-6)
        - Pre-Print Master Elements, Archival Resource Key
          - Reel 1, undated; 1972; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel (4 film reels: A+B Roll picture and 2 soundtrack reels) (Item FC 215)
            (Can with A Roll contains film lab records)
            - Reel 1, A-roll picture, 1972; 1974; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 213)
            - Reel 1, B-roll picture, 1972; 1974; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 214)
            - Reel 1, soundtrack mix, Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 216)
          - Reel 2, 1972; 1974; 1976; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm
            - Reel 2, Effects Soundtrack A, 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 217)
            - Reel 2. Effects Soundtrack C, 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 218)
            - Reel 2, Effects Soundtrack D, 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 219)
            - Reel 2, Effects Soundtrack B, 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 220)
          - Reel 2, Archival Resource Key (Item FC 221)
            - Reel 2 B-roll picture, 1972-1976; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 222)
            - Reel 2 Dialogue soundtrack B, 1972-1976; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 223)
            - Reel 2 Dialogue soundtrack A, 1972-1976; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 224)
            - Reel 2 Effects soundtrack E, 1972-1976; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 225)
            - Reel 2 Narration soundtrack, 1972-1976; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 226)
            - Reel 2 Music soundtrack, 1972-1976; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 227)
            - Reel 2 Duplicate soundtrack, 1972-1976; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 228)
          - Reels 1 and 2, 1978-1980; 1976; Archival Resource Key; (4 film reels: internegative picture and soundtrack) (Item FC 229-232)
            - Reel 1. internegative picture, 1976-1980; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 229)
            - Reel 1, internegative sound, 1976-1980; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 230)
          - Reel 1, 1991; Archival Resource Key; (2 film reels: internegative picture and soundtrack) (Item FC 233-234)
            - Reel 1, internegative picture, 1991; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 233)
      - Production Elements, Archival Resource Key
        - Original Ending, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel (9 film reels: A+B Roll picture, internegative picture and soundtrack, and answer print, housed in 2 film cans) (Item FC 238-243)
          - Original End Section, 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 237)
        - Revised Ending, 1977; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 28, Item 9-10)
        - Parts I, II, and III, circa 1977; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound tape reels (Box 28, Item 11-13)
        - Titles, 1977; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 244)
        - Pre-print with Visible Time Code, 1991; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 32, Folder 7-8)
        - Pre-print with Visible Time Code, 1991; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 33, Folder 1)
        - Original Ending, soundtrack, 1972; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 235)
        - Original Ending, motion picture, 1972; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 236)
      - Excerpts, Archival Resource Key
        - Two Segments: Bellerophon Taming Pegasus, Freedom of Expression, circa 1977; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 33, Folder 2)
        - Stills and Segments for Random House Presentation, 1994; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (BetacamSP) (Box 33, Folder 3)
      - Television Coverage, Archival Resource Key
        - Today Show, 1977-06-16; Archival Resource Key
          - Today Show, 1977-06-16; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 306)
          - Today Show, 1977 June 16; Archival Resource Key; (1 film reel, 1 duplicate videocassette: U-Matic, film reel housed in Box 65) (Box 33, Folder 4)
        - News Story on Bellerophon Taming Pegasus Installation, 1977; Archival Resource Key
          - News Story on Bellerophon Taming Pegasus Installation, 1977; Archival Resource Key; (1 film reel, 1 duplicate videocassette: U-Matic, film reel housed in Box 65) (Box 33, Folder 5)
            (Film can contains film lab records)
          - Television Coverage 1977, reel 1, Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 307)
          - Television Coverage 1977, reel 2, Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 308)
  - Other Projects, 1961-2000; 2.6; Archival Resource Key; 5.2 Linear feet Boxes 47-52, 66-67
    This subseries contains audiovisual material and a few paper records from projects unrelated to Jacques Lipchitz that were also found among Bruce Bassett's papers. Other projects by Bruce Bassett include audiovisual recordings from projects about Isamu Noguchi, Sidney Lifchez, Auguste Rodin, the Storm King sculpture center, IBM, and others, listed below. The Lifchez documentary is well-documented, but records of other projects in the series are incomplete and fragmentary. Also found are projects by others, including a draft of a screenplay, two news films of John F. Kennedy, and several other film titles. The films Dream on Monkey Mountain and Man Is My Name were made by others but were produced or aired by NBC, where Bassett worked, and he may have been involved in their production or broadcast.
    - Projects by Bruce Bassett, Archival Resource Key
      - A House for Someone Unlike Me with Sidney Lifchez, Archival Resource Key
        - Finished Version, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (1 videocassette: U-Matic, 2 duplicate videocassettes: VHS); 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 33, Folder 6-7)
        - 15-minute Version, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 34, Folder 1)
        - Camera Tapes 1-22, 1984; Archival Resource Key; (22 of 25 videocassettes: VHS) (Box 34, Item 2-23)
        - Camera Tapes 23-25, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 3 of 25 videocassettes: VHS) (Box 35, Item 1-3)
      - IBM Project, Archival Resource Key
        - The Massey Ferguson Project, 1983; Archival Resource Key; (3 film reels: color negative, internegative, and soundtrack) (Item FC 247)
          (Color negative can contains film lab records)
          - Color negative reel, 1983; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel no picture, only sound present 16mm (Item FC 245)
          - Internegative reel, 1983; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 246)
          - Soundtrack reel, 1983; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Track 16mm (Item FC 247)
        - Interactive Marketing Project, 1982; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 35, Folder 4)
        - Computer Search and Retrieval Instructions, undated; Archival Resource Key; (1 sound tape reel and paper file) (Box 35, Folder 5)
        - Interviews, 1982; Archival Resource Key; (1 sound cassette, 2 annotated, empty cassette cases) (Box 35, Folder 6)
        - Unidentified Video, Reels 3, 1986 June 17; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1 inch) (Item 318)
        - Unidentified Video, Reel 4, 1986-06-17; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1 inch) (Item 319)
      - Isamu Nogochi Project, Archival Resource Key
        - Sound Rolls 1-3, 1978 September 12-15; Archival Resource Key (Box 35, Item 7-9)
        - Momo Taro, 1979 January 4; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 35, Item 10)
        - Detroit Fountain, circa 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 35, Item 11)
        - Honolulu Rolls 2, 5, and 7, circa 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key; 4 Sound cassettes (Box 35, Item 12-15)
          (2 cassettes are marked "roll 2")
        - First Half, Soundtrack, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Contains Magnetic Sound (Item FC 248)
        - Unidentified Video, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (2 inch) (Item 320)
          (Label reads "1-12 Lipchitz, 13-24 Noguchi")
      - Rodin-related Interviews, Archival Resource Key
        - Jean Bernard, undated; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 35, Item 16-17)
        - Jean Dubos, undated; Archival Resource Key; (1 side of 1 sound cassette) (Box 35, Item 18)
        - Ernest Menten, undated; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (3 sides of 2 sound cassettes) (Box 35, Item 18-19)
        - Jean Dubos and Ernest Menten, undated; Archival Resource Key; (1 side of 1 sound cassette) (Box 35, Item 20)
        - Pierre Vivant, 1981 January 22; Archival Resource Key; (1 side of 1 sound cassette) (Box 35, Item 20)
        - Cecile Goldscheider of the Musée Rodin, 1979; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 35, Item 21)
          (In French)
        - Kirk Varnadoe, 1980 May 14; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 35, Item 22)
        - Pierre Vivant, undated; June 1979; Archival Resource Key; 7 Sound tape reels (Box 35, Item 23-29)
          (Identified within recordings as camera reels 315, 316, 318, 320, 322, 326, 357; location of camera reels unknown)
        - Pierre Vivant, 1981 May 10-11; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 35, Folder 30)
      - Unidentified Sound Cassette, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 35, Folder 31)
      - Sculptors at Storm King, 1992-2000; Archival Resource Key; 5 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 36, Item 1-5)
        (Includes multiple versions; also known as Peter Stern's Storm King)
      - Peter Stern Interview, 2000; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) silent (Box 36, Item 6)
      - Book of Kells, 2000; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (2 videocassettes: VHS, 1 videocassette: Betacam SP) (Box 36, Item 7-9)
      - Citibank Commerical, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 36, Item 10)
      - Matteo Ricci, 1991; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 249)
    - Projects by Others, Archival Resource Key
      - Buffalo Rock, Ottawa, IL, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 315)
      - Eames and Lipchitz, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 36, Item 11)
        (Contains films by Charles and Ray Eames and copy of Bassett's Lipchitz film)
      - John F. Kennedy News Films, Archival Resource Key
        - President Kennedy's News Conference #12, 1961 June 28; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 316)
          (Contains transcript)
        - Conversation with President Kennedy, 1962 February 7; Archival Resource Key (Box 37, Folder 1)
        - Conversation with President Kennedy reel 1, 1963; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 311)
        - Conversation with President Kennedy, reel 2, 1963; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 312)
      - Man is My Name by Pierre Dominique Gaisseau, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 313)
      - The Man with Two Sides to His Head by Anthony Cave Brown, Archival Resource Key
        - Draft of Screenplay, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 37, Folder 2-6)
        - Research, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 37, Folder 7)
      - NBC Experiment in Television: Dream on Monkey Mountain, part 2, 1970; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel (oversized reel in Box 67) (Item FC 314)
    - The Artist at Work "Jack Lipchitz Master Sculptor - Crescent", n.d.; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 317)